Guide to the Edward Hyde, Earl of Clarendon Correspondence
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3 ALS and 5 DS
1666-1684
OSBORN FB152
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.08
(1 volume)
Collection of manuscripts, in multiple hands, primarily documenting Clarendon's financial activities. Many of the items are acknowledgments of debts, including one appointing Sir Robert Clayton and John Morris to act as his attorneys in order to pay interest out of his shares of the New River Waterworks to his debtors; a legal document and several receipts acknowledging Clarendon's debts and payments to others arising from shares in the New River Waterworks; and three pages of financial accounts and calculations related to those debts and payments. Other items include a request to Clayton for a copy of his father's deed settling Clarendon House on Richard Boyle, Earl of Burlington, explaining that he is weighing offers of purchase from John Granville, Earl of Bath; Christopher Monck, Duke of Albemarle, and William Cavendish, Earl of Devonshire; a letter to Clayton asking him to appoint a house where they can meet with Richard Boyle and Alan Brodrick, 1st Viscount Midleton; and another to Clayton thanking him and John Morris for a bill of credit and promising him a gift of fruit trees, including some varieties not yet in England.
Clarendon, Edward Hyde, Earl of, 1609-1674
Immediate Source of Acquisition
For provenance information, consult the appropriate curator.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The following finding aid is a complete inventory of the contents of Osborn fb152. This list was reformatted from previously existing cataloging.
Finance, Personal -- England; Land tenure -- England; Legal documents; Stocks -- England; Great Britain -- Social life and customs -- 17th century; Accounts; Correspondence; Albemarle, Christopher Monck, Duke of, 1653-1688; Bath, John Grenville, Earl of, 1628-1701; Brodrick, Alan, Viscount Midleton, 1656?-1728; Burlington, Richard Boyle, Earl of, 1612-1698; Clarendon, Edward Hyde, Earl of, 1609-1674; Clayton, Robert, Sir, 1629-1707; Devonshire, William Cavendish, Earl of, 1617-1684; Keck, Anthony, Sir, 1630-1695
- Osborn fb152
  - [VERDICT IN THE CASE OF DOVE VS. PRETYMAN]
    - Document, signed (Box 1)
      Scope and Contents
      1 p; 31 x 25 cm.
      Document addressed to Clarendon as
      "Lord High Chancellor of England"
      from Sir Robert Clayton (1629-1707)
      and John Morris. Concerns a land
      dispute. Signed by Clayton,
      Morris and Clarendon.
      Dove, John.
  - CLARENDON, EDWARD HYDE, 1ST EARL OF, 1609-74
    - ALS to Sir Robert Clayton (1629-1707), 1675 Jul 22 (Box 1)
      n.p.
      1 p.; 20 x 29 cm.
      Requests a copy of his father's deed
      settling Clarendon House on Richard
      Boyle, 1st Earl of Burlington
      (1612-98) and gives advice regarding
      the purchase offers of John
      Granville, 7th Earl of Bath
      (1628-1701); Christopher Monck, 2nd
      Duke of Albemarle (1653-88) and
      William Cavendish, 4th Earl of
      Devonshire (1617-84). With an ALS
      (1931 Sep 10) from Herbert Arthur\
      Doubleday (1867-1941) to J.C.K
      Letts-Croke, regarding Clarendon's
      letter.
  - CLARENDON, EDWARD HYDE, 1ST EARL OF, 1609-74
    - Document, signed (Box 1)
      1 p.; 37 x 24 cm.
      Acknowledges debts to several people
      and appoints Sir Robert Clayton and
      John Morris as his attorneys. Signed
      by Morris, Thomas Leman and Sir
      Anthony Keck (1630-95).
  - CLARENDON, EDWARD HYDE, 1ST EARL OF, 1609-74
    - ALS to Sir Robert Clayton., 1675 Dec 16 (Box 1)
      London.
      1 p.; 20 x 30 cm.
      Asks Clayton to appoint a house where
      they can meet with Richard Boyle, 1st
      Earl of Burlington (1612-98) and Sir
      Alan Brodrick, 1st Viscount Midleton
      (1656?-1728).
  - CLARENDON, EDWARD HYDE, 1ST EARL OF, 1609-74
    - ALS to Sir Robert Clayton., 1676 Sep 30 (Box 1)
      1 p.; 33 x 22 cm.
      Thanks him and John Morris for a bill
      of credit and promises to return to
      London with a parcel of Fruit Trees.
  - CLARENDON, EDWARD HYDE, 1ST EARL OF, 1609-74
    - Document, signed (Box 1)
      1 p.; 42 x 33 cm.
      Acknowledges debts and payments to
      Sir Robert Clayton, Sir Anthony Keck
      (1630-95) and others, witnessed by
      Keck and Deane Monteage.
  - CLARENDON, EDWARD HYDE, 1ST EARL OF, 1609-74
    - Document, signed (Box 1)
      1 p.; 31 x 19 cm.
      Acknowledges debt, stated by Sir
      Robert Clayton, to Sir Anthony Keck,
      witnessed by Keck and Deane Monteage.
  - CLARENDON, EDWARD HYDE, 1ST EARL OF, 1609-74
    - Document, signed (Box 1)
      1 p.; 30 x 18 cm.
      Acknowledges debts computed by Sir
      Robert Clayton to Sir Anthony Keck
      and others, witnessed by Keck and
      Thomas Beech, with 3 pages of
      figures.